okay oh I made the mistake of reading
YouTube comments don't ever do that it's
a horrible idea um stick with me here
okay so the web we talked about the web
already um and I'm going to talk
about one of the topics that people
fight about the most when it comes to
web technology in fact I would go so far
as to say that almost all of the
fights that happen about web related
Technologies and approaches to the Web
come down to a basic difference of
opinion and a different base usage for
the web so hear me out the web started
out as I did in another very long video
about the history of the web you can
watch it if you want go look at that the
web started out as a way to share email
bottom line put a whole bunch of email
on a server interpers some you know
clickable links in there with pictures
of c um
you know collisions and stuff like that
and you get the worldwide web that was
invented at certain by Tim burner Lee it
was basically a place to put documents
and it was a website website is a
collection of documents that have
pictures potentially and hyperlinks you
can click on there and go between the
documents that is the web that is the
fundamental use of the worldwide web and
one of my biggest complaints is that the
modern web in 2024 has become so much
more than that that we've kind of lost
track of the fact that the original
intent of the worldwide web was to share
static documentation that changed on
occasion but that wasn't it didn't
depend on some real time interaction it
was like give me the resources give me
the picture give me the text and then
show it to me and maybe I can even cash
it and keep it locally right so I have a
copy on my phone or something that was
the original intent to the worldwide web
it solved a big big problem how do we
share documents without spamming
everybody in email and it worked and it
still works to this day and if you go um
hear about Tim burners Le's complaints
about the web today his primary
complaint is that the web has lost its
way it just doesn't know about that base
usage of the web so what other ways are
is the web being used today and and how
is this creating um you know division
among web developers as well as just
absolute confusion and unusability in
the web so so the very first usage of
the web and I think it should still be
the primary usage is for document
exchange that means you take a document
and I mean a document with sections
articles and everything and we'll get
into that in another video when we talk
about HTML markdown exchanging documents
rich media documents documents that may
have a picture or something in there but
for the most part they're the kind of
documents that could be printed into a
book and you could use the book instead
right that's the fundamental use to the
web now that kind of grew right the
first time somebody wanted an
interactive graph right then that
document kind of changed because that
interactive graph where you can change
the numbers on the graph and stuff
started turning it wasn't in document
anymore at that point right because even
though there might be a way to print it
you know being able to interact with the
graph and change the numbers or drag and
drop now that's no longer a document now
it's kind of an application right and
this is the beginning of the biggest
division in the entire internet when it
comes to the worldwide web is that you
have people that are making apps and you
have people that are making documents
and you have people that are mixing the
two up and um and so that becomes a
really bad problem because now you have
content you know that could otherwise be
consumed like documents and I remember I
don't know if this is still true but at
one point I won't say the language but
there was one particular language that
had a documentation site that could not
be viewed without JavaScript support and
when we get when we get down later on
when we start talking about the terminal
we're going to talk about using um
research uh tools from the terminal such
as links and w3m and how to do text
based browsing people will think why
would I ever do that the main reason to
do that is because I can I can find
things in a fraction of the time we're
talking 130th or 1/ 100th of the time
that it takes somebody to do with a
graphic based web browser and I'll show
you how to do that because you want to
be able to get that research as fast as
possible in the world with Chad GPT
still being able to search the worldwide
web from the command line is extremely
valuable but when your language or your
site or your blog decides to create a
JavaScript dependency for what is
otherwise an article and a document just
so that it can be rendered properly
you've now stopped that from being used
not only that you probably violated a
number of things that allow it to be
viewed by those who are blind or death
and we will talk about that a little bit
later perhaps in a video about all the
people including Pizza Hut who was sued
and lost um by the the by the the blind
community and others because their site
was not did not was was an app and it
didn't need to be an app okay so we have
the document web and we have the what I
call the app web this is just as
populated by div soup which we'll talk
about when we get into HTML but it's
mostly it's turned the web worldwide web
into a
a framework for Distributing web
applications and I think that's fine the
problem is is as I said already is the
mixing of the document web with the app
web when you mix those two together you
get something that neither is a very
good web app nor can it be used as a
document right and so the the The Plea
that I will put right now in this video
is don't mix the two when possible
separate out the your documentation from
thank you for the happy happy separate
out your documentation from your apps
okay because because if you have if you
have you can have your interactive
awesome app thing it's one of the
reasons that I like view so much because
view is very modular you can have an
interactive element of your document and
it doesn't kill the rest of your
document it still displays and can you
know view source is is readable and all
of that okay so you have the document
web and you have the app web right and
there's still I think there's there's
two other forms of web that are emerging
um there's the streaming web uh or the
rich media web and that includes uh I
mean people forget this but you know uh
Netflix Disney um you know Amazon Prime
I mean when you go to use Amazon Prime
you don't even realize you're using the
web anymore but that is all web Tech
right so we have what I would call the
streaming web uh or you know the content
delivery web stream but call it the
streaming web the streaming web is
largely this what you're watching right
now you're watching multimedia videos
it's basically the broadcast web um
streaming broadcast whatever you want to
call it it is web Tech I know it's hard
to believe but you are now participating
in web technology but you almost change
your your brain mode when you go to
consume that kind of web right you're
like no I'm using it's like my my
replacement for you know the radio or
the TV it's it's the streaming web it's
the it's the broadcasting web and I I
still feel like um that that is a part
of a part of the web um hyper yeah hyper
media goes back to the 60s absolutely um
but berners Le didn't invent it he just
applied that technique that's a good
clarification thank you Ronnie so so we
have those three types right now I
believe that there is a third type of
web and this you could call I used to
call it the conversational web um but I
would call it the AI web and the the AI
web is just the web being used as an
excuse to convey AI information and um
whether it be
autogenerated um I mean it kind of
overlaps with the application web but I
I feel like it's the web as a transport
medium for AI and and it's it's
basically our method of querying uh AI
so more and more the big like the chat
gbts and the Geminis and the Googles and
all that these these things are coming
about and we are talking to them and
they are answering us so there's kind of
like this AI web which is its own thing
in my opinion um you know it's being
totally backed by AI engines and the
method of of of con you know the method
that it communicates with us is sort of
based on some of the app web and other
things like that but it's fundamentally
about the inter interacting with AI and
and that we're going to see AI hit all
the other areas but I you could also
call this this is the AI web I would
have called conversational web before or
the search web right um that is its own
Beast right it's its own Beast being
able to query and get data out of the
web and get it back that that is you
know it's yes it's an app it's not
really a document right it's formatted
in documents but it's it's largely about
provide the web itself is providing the
front end to data query uh and in this
in this day age that that data querying
is AI web so that would be the fourth
major category for the web that I would
put so the four categories for me are um
the document web the original web the
app web which is the web as a transport
medium for
applications um the streaming web or the
broadcast web uh that includes radio and
video like this and you know the query
web or the AI web which is I'm I'm
getting data and I want data back
whatever that is and usually there's
going to be an AI or there's some large
amount of data query involved there
those are the four types of web and as
we go into web development you know when
the reason I have to clarify what the
different uses of the web are the
primary uses and and when we because
when we talk about web deild and people
are always like what are you talking
about making a basic website does that
mean I have to know how to do X or Y I'm
like no that we're just talking about
making a document so so that I have to
say we're not going to be making apps
like what what do you mean we you're not
learning JavaScript I can't make a
website without JavaScript you
absolutely can you can make a web
document without it right and that is
the fundamental reason for this video uh
proceed to leave your negative comments
below if you
disagree I'm having a bad day okay talk
to you later